if you join the business Buyers Club and
you listen to the acquisitive podcast
and you go to deal Academy mhm like it's
cheaper than an
NBA I know like you will close on a
business like it'll happen can we
guarantee it legally um yeah I see no
problem of course
not y'all think too small I got Big
Dreams you just stting them way ahead at
the end
started reading and dodging all the
quick like your sptify boy I got streams
real big I got to make it for my
kids hi I'm Sarah I'm Daniel and this is
acquisitive where we break down failed
acquisition deals to make sure you make
it all the way to the closing table this
is episode two three two two and our
guest today is Shannon hey Shannon hay
is senior vice president of commercial
lending and accounting firm acquisition
specialist he provides competitive
financing solutions to accounting and
tax professionals Across the Nation and
he has assisted with over 350 accounting
firm Acquisitions is that number
accurate Shannon or has
it we're uh we're approaching 400 yeah
we're getting real close to 400 about
350 million totally did you get that
from Shannon ahead of time or is that
how you introduce him every time you
guys do a call together it is it's
actually yeah I made it up so it's not
even I've been counting personally I've
been I have a little ticker um yeah
thanks S I appreciate you keeping track
for me oh you're welcome you're welcome
I enjoy it on a more personal note
Shannon I have talked to you know
infinite people at this point who have
worked with you and universally they
always say he's so generous with his
time and that's certainly what I found
too you just you answer the phone you
take longer than probably anybody would
to describe things you seem personally
invested in people's success it's
fantastic you're great to work with
everybody enjoys it I appreciate that
you know like those funny little uh
posts you see on social media where is
like like if you were kidnapped and you
had to call somebody who you knew would
answer or you're gonna get it who would
you call mine is Shannon
hey that's great I'm your Lifeline
Daniel you would be my lifeline I love
that I love I'm not a master trivia so
please do not okay so Know Who Wants To
Be A Millionaire call cannot be yeah I
mean I don't know maybe rock and roll
questions you know some I think more
relatedly do you keep like a good stash
of bail money
available I I got you Daniel no problem
okay you know he's a former bail
bondsman so that's probably where he's
thinking maybe I should memorize your
phone number you can be in a he probably
knows he probably knows more people than
I than you know than I
do well Shannon we were hoping you would
tell us kind of one example of a deal
that didn't make it to closing and we
could dissect it and go from there
because as you know there's a ton of
vanity metrics all over the internet
that are like oh I I bought an HVAC
company in Louisiana and now I live on a
sailboat in the Bahamas and work 15
minutes a week you too can make that
happen just get a 7A loan zero money
down yeah yeah subscribe to my channel
uh uhuh and that's I mean I'm like
subscribe every time so I'm completely
vulnerable to that market
approach but at the same time you know
as a lawyer who sees dozens and dozens
and dozens of these all the time um they
don't usually I've not actually had a
single call with somebody from a
sailboat yet so where are these people
well I talked to a guy uh actually the
other day in a van he was he lived in a
van and he owned he had his own virtual
firm doing about 100K and he's looking
to you know buy another buy another
virtual firm but Shannon I had lunch
with him on Monday
you did didn't
you yeah what
a he had he had stayed at the 24-Hour
Fitness the night before perfect so
pretty good clean shaven then yeah clean
shaven that's so funny that you brought
him I was just thinking of
him so as you can see it's a small world
in um you know accounting uh
Acquisitions are my specialty too
largely thanks to Shannon so and um is
that an example that you have for us is
it an accounting practice that didn't
make it to
closing no no um so there you know
there's tons of reasons why people don't
make it to closing and and you know we
could certainly nail down an exact
example but I think it' probably be
better to just you know talk about what
are the circumstance because there's a
there's a common theme right it's not um
it's not as if this is you know it's not
it well first of all what do we always
say time kills deals right so if you're
slow if you're slow to react to the the
the listing itself you're slow to you
know make an offer um if you you know
don't hesitate right in this market it's
such a fast-moving Market that you
really if if you're excited about
something you've really got to get
moving on it because the the deals don't
stick around um you know everything
after that right the but the letter of
intense the critical moment right and
then that's where the clarity has to be
if if there isn't Clarity around the
letter of intent you don't have your
structure laid out your understanding of
a what what a non-compete looks like
what's the transition post transition
agreement going to look like um you have
to talk about those things because all
those variables tied in the in a
standard letter of intent we won't we
don't have to make it a complicated one
um are critical to the process right and
that's the key element is communication
breakdown right is that if you're not
clearly communicating your needs and
you're not clearly understanding the
seller's needs you're you're going to
have a hard time getting to the closing
table that Mak sense in you're speaking
my language because I'm obsessed with
the
LOI so and I think most things can be
solved there it's like absolute so give
us an example what is most you know
anonymize it obviously but the most
recent deal that didn't make it to
closing that you saw what killed
it just that a misunderstanding of what
the expectations were of the seller and
the buyer um you know it's it's so
strange what what we believe as a buyer
our expectations might
be compared to what the sellers is and
then once you start to get if you don't
have that generalized in the LOI that
for example are you buying the are you
buying all rights are you buying the
full name of the entity are you buying
the website are you buying the phone
number that are you buying are if you're
buying the Goodwill what do you define
as
Goodwill um and be clear about that
because it's some you know some sellers
may have a a the one I the one I lost
the the seller thought that they could
keep the name of the because they want
to keep the name of the company because
it was their name right um they didn't
want to they didn't want to sell that
but it was like no I'm buying rights to
that name and I want the rights to that
name so that I can utilize that for
future marketing you know what have you
um there was a big confusion between
what the buyer and seller thought was
appropriate there and it broke the deal
in a deal like that in a situation like
that where was the breakdown or what was
the missing piece is that something that
you know maybe there should have been an
intermediary on both sides or they
should have engaged someone sooner yeah
I you know the intermediary um
definitely wasn't um I I guess clear
with what they thought but the the
seller wasn't clear to their
intermediary what they expected and I
don't think that the intermediary was
clear to them as what the expectation in
the marketplace was right so um we all
understand that in a Goodwill
transaction we're buying the secret
sauce right and sometimes that's a
website um sometimes you know it it is
um gosh it it could be simple thing the
location itself whatever it might be but
just make sure that it's that it's you
know clear right at what point on the
process did that come up like that's a
pretty threshold issue yeah yeah no
actually it was it was not clear in the
LOI right that that was the expectation
and then um between that and the asset
purchas agreement once the asset
purchase agreement started what I call
grinding out right or grinding you know
grinding against the you know the deal
itself that's you know the
details floated to the top and and and
the the lack of expectation
communication on both sides fell apart
um the it was strange to me I think the
seller even thought they were keeping
their website which sort of blew me away
a little bit I I I you I'm like you've
been advertising and monitoring and
absorbing clients in that portal on that
website and you you you don't think
you're selling that as part of the
business like that flows directly to
your tax return my opinion as a banker
and when the when the buyer said that to
me I said you you need to walk away
right you you're not you're not buying
the
practice you know this is fascinating
because so we talked a lot about
preparing you know preparing for
acquisitive and uh talking about deals
that fail we talked a lot about
different times in the process or in the
timeline where things can go sideways
and often we talked about kind of these
surprises these like landmines that you
just St on but what you mentioned is
something that that is even more
fascinating than than we had even talked
about previously where you know Sarah
you mentioned that that this is a
threshold issue like this is like you
know first meeting with buyer and seller
we should lay out
expectations but it didn't actually
become an issue and throughout the deal
sideways until the asset purchase
agreement almost you know at toward days
toward the end 30 days into yeah we had
full we had full loan approval um
commitment letter has been issued we
were in
closing um and you know buyer and seller
didn't didn't agree on the the
terminology and and expectations of the
asset purchase but it was not you know
and I don't know do you say I I I don't
think it this one was a hard one right
because you know the buyer has a you
know a threshold of expectation right
that that should that we think is normal
right we all agree website phone number
name should all be included in that
acquisition we just assume that everyone
would think that um and he did too
um and you know once the seller it was
time to like give up that piece of the
pie they they were like oh no no no I I
don't I don't want to let go of my
namesake right I might use that down the
road
for I guess beyond my non-compete
because that was the that was the
confusing part too is like well then
where does
that the non-compete restrictive
covenants you know non-solicit
agreements was the seller retiring or no
and that's what made it even more you
know tumultuous right and and why we
kind of said you know buyer you probably
should walk away yeah my my little
anecdote that I say all the time which
is true and I can't remember if you were
on this deal or not but my most heavily
negotiated non-compete was with a guy
who was 90
so so great you know and and similar
maybe in this situation it wasn't about
the non-compete it was about his own
feelings about retire iring and
relevancy and probably his relationship
with his spouse and a lot of other
things and um Chuck Hayes uh A really
lovely broker he he gave me a lot of
insight once um many times but this one
time he was talking about how uh
sometimes he'll have a seller that is
just you know unpredictably foot
dragging and they're ready and he talks
to them and they're ready but then they
sleep on it they come back they're less
ready to sell and he isolated that it's
the spouse usually who's not ready for
them to sell who less comfortable with
the financial Outlook of having um them
not work or maybe they don't really want
them in the house all the time and so
they're kind of getting in their mind a
little bit and causing this uh hard to
really pinpoint um hesitancy that comes
up in weird unexpected ways like hey I
want to keep my website it's really
important to me um so sometimes maybe
it's not about the website maybe it's
not about the name no it and that's just
an example right there's there's there's
a lot of heartstrings when you're
especially when you're speaking to you
know most firm owners now that are are
retiring or are selling they they've
operated that for 35 years right 40
years 45 years right so there you know
there's a lot of Blood Sweat and Tears
and and you're as a buyer it you know
that's where it's key that you have to
really almost to cater to those
expectations right cater to that emotion
um try to understand what those feelings
are ahead of time right what are their
needs right maybe they maybe they do
want to still come around during tax
season and you know hang out and run a
couple returns right I mean
that it's kind of I don't know I guess
it's I don't do tax returns but maybe
it's like playing the piano right you
know once you know how to do it you
always want to do it I I I don't I'm not
sure but do you play the piano I no I
play the guitar a little bit but but I
but you always you know it's like the
guitar similarly to a piano I guess is
that you know you you don't maybe never
you're never an expert at it but you
always want to pick it up right um and I
think that sometimes this is their it's
it's tax
prepared they're they're it's a hobby to
them a little bit right it's a passion
so I don't think I'll ever stop being
involved in selling accounting firms
right it's it's what I do it's what I'm
passionate about it's what I you know I
yeah I mean when everyone when
everyone's not counting on you anymore
when once you removed yourself from the
firm and you know the clients aren't
calling looking for you the team's not
looking to you for guidance uh then
getting back to doing the tax return
work you know it's uh I would imagine I
don't particularly enjoy but I don't
know maybe it's like Suduko you know
yeah yeah there you go another great
example just they're just on their
phones doing tax returns in a soothing
way at night yeah and when you're a firm
owner especially if you've been a firm
owner for decades you know you probably
think back to your your first few years
in the industry where you were just by
yourself sitting there grinding through
a tax return without you know your phone
blowing up your emails stacking up with
unread messages um so you kind of go
back to the beginning and just get back
to the fundamentals yeah which which is
actually the take away that I'm I'm
getting from this uh I'm by far by far
the the newest to the world of mergers
and Acquisitions uh here amongst us and
uh so I've been learning the
fundamentals and that's pretty much been
my main focus but just like professional
athletes constantly train on the
fundamentals I think this is a great
reason for beginner dealmakers
experienced dealmakers and especially
mergers and acquisition experts to
remember the fundamentals and remember
the value in having a checklist you know
maybe you have that checklist that of
all the intangible assets and you have
every single buyer go through it every
single seller go through it and it it
feels like just another thing to do deal
over deal over deal but when you do it
you can get out ahead of these things
and you can set expectations and move
the process faster well Daniel you you
know you've kind of went through this a
little bit recently right is the there
you know there's a seller has these
expectations that you think that you
think start out realistically but then
quickly turn unrealistic
and do you do you feel like maybe they I
I don't to me it's a it is a feeling
right there's an emotion it's a Kumbaya
moment you've got to find a a way to
connect yeah
um and and I think that it's it's not
always easy to do that right it's not
it's it's a big part of why my deal went
sideways I think uh I mean there were
other factors at play and we talked
about my deal last week so oh cool sorry
I missed that yeah I was focused on the
financial elements that that sent the
deal sideways but time was a huge issue
for us and because we didn't do a great
job at setting expectations during my my
meeting with the seller and because we
only had one seller meeting I probably
should have had a
followup um You Know lesson learned for
next time uh but we we found that we
were setting expectations and aligning
on those expectations with the LOI so I
would draft an Loi he would sign it and
then he'd think about it and come back
and say Hey you know by the way I don't
want that or I don't agree with this so
then we're throwing the LOI out and then
we're and then I was redrafting it
updating it um and that went on for for
weeks and um and you know you get to the
fourth iteration of the LOI and then and
then he goes and then we're back to the
the reason the first one was thrown out
like oh you you know you have to change
the name like no I want your name uh we
already talked about this right so
what's the was your deal brokered was it
listed or was it yes okay yeah it was
brokered I mean that's a skill that some
of these Brokers get very good at is
this figuring out who you might even
know who I'm talking about who's a real
seller you know who's a true seller and
um you know some some people aren't
ready just as I saying it's a manage the
emotions moment right you you really but
the emotions are are tied to all those
variables right the Legacy the
financials the you know the non-
competes the
transition So Many Factors I had a call
with somebody at some point in the world
I'll anonymize it enough and very recent
top of mine and um they were a buyer at
talking about how you know the sellers
very on board for my plans to you know
grow and expand and create an empire and
I was like maybe you don't talk about
that as much with the seller you know um
that's not necessarily the seller's
interest I think it's very important to
empathetically view it from the seller's
perspective it doesn't really matter if
you take it to the moon they're out of
the equation there's no kind of rollover
Equity situation in this particular deal
and in a way it can come across critical
because you're saying what did you do
wrong why didn't you grow it like this
or uh you know and I gave her the
example I said it's like if you're going
through a house with the the person who
owns it and saying love this house can't
wait to gut the kitchen I'm gonna
totally tear it apart you know it it can
be emotional and offensive yeah it's the
big and it's a big deal it's your it's
their yeah it might be another it might
be another acquisition to you right it's
a very emotional moment for them yeah I
think keeping yourself- centered as the
buyer on hey to the seller this is like
you said their legacy this is their um
security for retirement purposes and
it's you know somebody stepping in to
take care of their employees and their
clients and that's really what they
usually care about so dial it back on
the other stuff right yeah you don't
want to tell them you're Outsourcing
them to India yeah that's like we're
just do that later hire all the staff
I'm Outsource all the tax return it's
going to be great I'm going to make so
much money
and there's there's an infinite number
of personality types out there so it's
you know sometimes you'll tell a firm
owner that you want to house Force to
India and they'll say that sounds great
I've always thought about that and
they're genuine sometimes they're like
oh no my business will die if you do
that sometimes they'll say that's a
great idea and in the back of their mind
they're like that is horrible this
person's going to kill my business but
they don't want to be rude to you to
your face so they'll just say what you
want to hear and lure you into that
false sense of security so it's
definitely better to play close to the
vest when you're talking about what
you're GNA change there's nothing to be
gained by it that I can figure out yeah
it's your plan it's not theirs yeah um
well this has been really helpful
Shannon thanks yeah well find out what
their plan is and then suit that and
Brokers aren't going to do that for you
you know yeah they've got too many of
them they don't have time to sort that
out is that a case is that a case for
having a buy side broker even in these
smaller deals
um gosh no but I it just that just make
it's there's enough one intermediator is
enough frankly in my opinion but um buy
side representation as far as a a bank
that's been through it and an attorney
that's been through it yeah I think so
but but you have to find it you have to
find a banker and an attorney like like
the two of you where would you find find
that where would you even
start but I would say you know
experienced team is is critical but I
wouldn't you know a lot of Brokers
aren't there's not a lot of buy
representation out there in the
intermediary world it's you know if you
talk to them their minimum fees are are
so high even on the sell side that it
doesn't behoove them to represent the
buy side now I don't want to I don't
want to say that's that doesn't exist or
that service isn't available I just I
think that you're going to find that
that a lot of the brokers in this world
um don't want to work with anybody else
and they hear another broker they're
going to that's just they're if they
have three buyers and one has has a
broker rep and the other two don't
they're going to take the buyers that
don't yeah well and so here's here's
where I fall back on being the novice
novice again uh I was just reading m&a
for dummies and uh there was this whole
section it's a great book I I definitely
I'm going to keep it around I'm gon to
re revisit it just you're turning it
backwards on your
bookshelf yeah you know I no I mean I
it's a good book it's a it's a great
in-depth breakdown to the process and
it's focused on uh small lower mid
midsize businesses so bigger deals than
I will get into anytime soon but there
was a whole section on just the ethics
around having a buy side a buy side
intermediary and having a sell's
intermediary who doesn't want to work
with a buyer who has an intermediary is
being a pretty major ethical issue so
well it's an interesting
perspective yeah it's the the funny
thing is though is we're coming into a
market that was built before we got here
right and you you know I didn't I didn't
draw the lines and the s or make the
rules it's um but it's what and I agree
with you wholeheartedly I I but again if
you're you're a selling broker and you
get to influence right are you going to
influence somebody
money well right you don't to split the
there yeah splitting split yeah oh gosh
that's a we could really get into a lot
of dialogue there I probably
should next time when we have you
back yeah that I mean you're you're
right and I've encountered a lot of
intermediaries or at least one who uh
very much uh dis disincentivizes even
having counsel lawyers and that feels
very uh ethically dubious so I I got
that that last deal I was on the the
broker he was he helped me and hurt me
in so many different ways throughout
that the course of that deal um but that
was something that he was like yeah you
don't need an attorney I have a
templated asset purchase agreement you
can just use this and 100% of the deals
that I've ever done have been on this
purchase agreement so if you don't sign
it immediately get out right if it's the
if it's the broker I'm thinking of which
is uh you know it's problem it's a
different one but I know which one
you're thinking of
Sarah no this is this is not the L this
is not the Lo asset purchas okay well
that's helpful yeah it's a small world
but I get it I mean I I honestly I
understand attorneys are the worst we we
have we're such a loose cannon uh to
throw in the middle of a deal that seems
like it's going well and you just never
know how it's going to shape up well um
you know time kills deals and so do
attorneys I know when you said that
earlier you said time kills deals and I
was like I'm used to you saying
attorneys
kill but that's why I try to be really
good with my song and dance of like it
wasn't
me well but that's also why it's
important to use somebody that's done it
over
more than once right an attorney that's
never seen an accounting deal before
yeah um oh yeah it's a different
situation right um practice makes
perfect and I don't keep you know I do
warn my clients like I don't keep
getting referrals by killing a bunch of
deals so I'm not gonna be I mean that
being said I'm the only person who is
supposed to get paid either way so I'll
tell you honestly but let's let's try
not to all right well I'm going to get
quotations on my on my my saying says
accept Sarah sharp oh I appreciate that
you're I do try but it is um I think the
ethics I would like to read I wish you
were closer Daniel I would swap books
with you I just read uh Harvard Business
reviews guide to buying a small business
I mean I could go for a vacation so yeah
why don't you yeah come on up here stay
at the cabin go
skiing that sounds great to me let's
let's reconvene after we get done
recording after the
all right well it was really nice to see
you Shannon thanks for all the insights
yeah Shannon thanks helpful thanks for
the takeaway where can everyone where do
you want everyone to find you and uh and
how can they work with you well you can
always find me on LinkedIn of course uh
I think I'm the only Shannon hay out
there that does Accounting in tax
lending and then um I'm on Twitter at
shba
Shay um or then email me Shay umwsb
docomo savingsbank.com wsb.com and then
uh 614 648 9199 because oh my God you
got to have the bat phone you got to
have the bat phone yeah memorize it if
you get arrested that's your first call
every listener I hope we get a lot of
downloads here and you have you might
have to change your phone number I'm not
concerned I'm not concerned all right
we'll we'll link it all wherever
wherever we post this live it's going to
be in the you know in the description
the show notes so you uh you know
everybody will be able to find you thank
you so much appreciate all right take
care shayen all right take care all
right so this has been inquisitive
episode number two with Shannon hay
talking about how time kills deals and
setting expectations can help you get to
the closing table thanks for listening
and subscribe wherever you're listening
to us big I got to make it just for my
kids for kids kids that's weth years and
years promise my brother soon as he to
fin this we do it bigger than anybody
ever